Finding Aid for the Collection of Material about Carey McWilliams, 1925-1948
UCLA Library Special Collections
Collection of Material about Carey McWilliams
1925-1948
2023
2 boxes (1.0 linear ft.)
Carey McWilliams (1905-1980) was a lawyer, author, and editor of The Nation. Some of his books include: Ambrose Bierce: A Biography (1929), Factories in the Field: The Story of Migratory Farm Labor in California (1939), Brothers Under the Skin: African Americans and Other Minorities (1943), Southern California Country: An Island on the Land (1946), and The Education of Carey McWilliams (1979). The collection consists primarily of newspaper clippings by and about McWilliams. Also includes some pamphlets and magazines.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF. Advance notice is required for access to the collection. Please contact UCLA Library Special Collections for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Unknown, ca. 1973.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4232757
Biography/History
Carey McWilliams was born December 13, 1905 in Steamboat Springs, Colorado. He received his JD from the University of Southern California and became an attorney at Black, Hammack & McWilliams, Los Angeles, 1927-38. He would go on to serve as chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing, State of California, 1938-42. He worked as an editor at The Nation from 1945 to 1975. Some of his books include: Ambrose Bierce: A Biography (1929), Factories in the Field: The Story of Migratory Farm Labor in California (1939), Ill Fares the Land: Migrants and Migratory Labor in the United States (1942), Brothers Under the Skin (1943), Prejudice: Japanese-Americans, Symbol of racial intolerance (1944), Southern California Country: An Island on the Land (1946), A Mask for Privilege: Anti-Semitism in America (1948), The Education of Carey McWilliams (1979). He died on June 27, 1980 in New York City.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of newspaper clippings by and about the California lawyer and author Carey McWilliams. It also includes some pamphlets and magazines. The clippings focus heavily on reviews of his work such as Mask of Privilege, Ill Fares the Land, North from Mexico, and Southern California Country: An Island on the Land. They also touch on the Thomas Jefferson award he received, as well as his dealings with the Committee on Un-American Activities in the 1940s. The collection also contains a number of McWilliams's published articles, reviews and commentaries.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
McWilliams, Carey, 1905-1980.; Authors, American --Sources.
Genres and Forms of Material
clippings.
Related Material
Carey McWilliams papers, 1894-1982 (Collection 1319). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Carey McWilliams papers, 1930-1940 (Collection 1243). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Carey McWilliams correspondence, 1924-1975 (Collection 1356). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Collection of materials by and about George Sterling, ca. 1901-1935 (Collection 276). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Carey McWilliams collection of material about Ambrose Bierce, 1842-ca. 1914 (Collection 277). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Carey McWilliams collection of material about Mary Hunter Austin, 1868-1934 (Collection 278). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Honorable in all things oral history transcript: the memoirs of Carey McWilliams [oral history transcript] / Carey McWilliams, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1978. Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Container List
- Press clippings, ca. 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Refer to Mask of Privilege, also included pamphlet for American Jewish Congress
- Press clippings, ca. 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Articles by and about Carey McWilliams and his work, including North from Mexico, Ill Fares the Land, 1972 reprint.
  Articles by McWilliams include:
  "Of Swords and Shields." Survey Graphic, April 1948.
  "First of El Dorado's Booms." New York Herald Tribune, April 3, 1949.
  "American Free Press Death by 'Postal Rate.'" Los Angeles Times, July 13, 1972, part II, page 7.
- Press clippings, ca. 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Articles by and about Carey McWilliams and his work, including references to North from Mexico and Mask of Privilege.
  "The Guy Who Gets Things Done." The Nation, July 9, 1949
  "Everything But Water." New York Herald Tribune, August 28, 1949 (book review)
  Copy of insurance policy
  Includes article by John Fante "Writer Rips Facts from the Jungle."
- Press clippings, ca. 1945-1973 (bulk 1948-9) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Clippings, pamphlet, magazine (issue of Jewish Life, August 1948), letter received from Bokförlaget Natur Och Kultur dated November 16, 1945.
  Materials by and about McWilliams, include mention of works such as Southern California Country: An Island on the Land, Mask of Privilege, North From Mexico.
  "The Senator Was Indiscreet." The Nation, March 13, 1948.
  "Equality or Fraternities?" Commentary, May, 1948.
  "Mexican Bundle of Myths." The Saturday Review, December 25, 1948.
  Program for America's Town Meeting broadcast, July 19, 1948.
- Press clippings, ca. 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Articles by and about McWilliams and his work, include mention of Mask of Privilege, North from Mexico.
  "The Rains Came." The Nation, March 27, 1948.
  "Old Story, New Guide."
  "This Boulevard Grew Up in a Hurry." New York Herald Tribune Weekly Book Review, September 25, 1949.
- Press clippings, pamphlet, program, and draft, ca. 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Clippings mention Mask of Privilege, North from Mexico.
  "A Play on History." Westways, May 1979.
  "What About Our Japanese Americans?" Public Affairs Committee pamphlet, undated.
  "Luisa Moreno Bemis," draft, August 1949.
- Press clippings, pamphlets, press release, correspondence and keepsake, ca. 1939-1948. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Works by Carey McWilliams include:
  "It CAN Happen Here," pamphlet, undated.
  "The Ongoing Discovery of California." Los Angeles Times, July 20, 1975.
  "Racism on the West Coast." The New Republic, May 29, 1944. (first of two articles on the topic)
  "Racism on the West Coast." The New Republic, June 12, 1944. (second of two articles on the topic)
  "Minority Groups in the United States." ORT Economic Review, August 1944.
  "Japanese Evacuation: Policy and Perspectives." Reprinted from Common Ground, Summer 1942.
  Press release dated March 4, 1941 on behalf of Division of Immigration and Housing. "West Coast Letter." The Chicago Jewish Forum, Fall 1948.
  "Minority Voters in American Politics." Jewish Frontier, September 1948.
  Works mentioned in press clippings include:
  Factories in the Field, Brothers Under the Skin, and Prejudice: Japanese-Americans, Symbol of Racial Intolerance
  Correspondence concerns Southern California Country
  Autograph book given as gift to McWilliams from the staff of the Santa Anita Pacemaker (September 11, 1942)
- McWilliams' early journal publications bound in book form, ca. 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  "Bierce as Poet." The Dumbook, Volume 1, Number 4, July 1925.
  "Old Fogy Attends a Concert." The Dumbook, Volume 1, Number 5, August 1925.
  "A Note on Anthony M. Ludovich." The Dumbook, Volume 1, Number 6-7, September-October 1925.
  "The Coral Comb." San Francisco Review, Volume 1, Number 8, November 1925.
  "The New Frank Norris." San Francisco Review, Volume 1, Numbers 9 and 10, January 1926.
  Review. San Francisco Review, Volume 2, Number 1, May 1926.
  Review. San Francisco Review, Volume 2, Number 4, December 1926.
  "Ambrose Bierce and Amateur Studies in Irony." The Wooden Horse, March 1924.
  "Notes on H.L. Mencken." The Wooden Horse, Winter, 1925.
- Pamphlets by Carey McWilliams (Box 2, Folder 2)
  "It CAN happen here," undated
  Race Discrimination and the Law," undated
  "Justice for Salcido" by Guy Endore, introduction by Carey McWilliams, undated
- Legal brief, ca. October 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- McWilliams, Carey. "The Nisei Speak." Common Ground, Summer 1944. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Promotion and marketing (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Factories in the Field review, pamphlet, November 1939.
  Southern California: An Island on the Land, order form, ca. 1974.
- ACLU Celebrates Freedom of the Press, December 8, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- McWilliams, Carey. "The Los Angeles Archipelago." Science and Society, Volume X, Number 1, Winter 1946. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Carey McWilliams in The American Mercury (Box 2, Folder 8)
  "Swell Letters in California." in The American Mercury, Volume XXI, Number 81, September 1930.
  "The Mystery of Ambrose Bierce." The American Mercury, Volume XXII, Number 87, March 1931.
- Magazine articles by Carey McWilliams (Box 2, Folder 9)
  "Mecca of the Miraculous." Holiday, January 1947.
  "Eirinn Go West." Westways, March 1978.
- Press clippings about Carey McWilliams., ca. 1946-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Mention of Mask of Privilege and North from Mexico.